<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                                              -->
<!--                                                                            -->
<!-- Logic and Proof for Teachers                                 -->
<!--                                                                            -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2019  Kimberly M. Childs, Deborah A. Pace, Thomas W. Judson  -->
<!--                                                                            -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.                               -->

<chapter xml:id="relations" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

<title>Relations</title>

    <assemblage>
        <title>TEXAS STATE BOARD FOR EDUCATOR CERTIFICATION (SBEC): MATHEMATICS STANDARDS COVERED</title>
        <p><ul>

            <li>STANDARD II: PATTERNS AND ALGEBRA: The mathematics teacher understands and uses patterns, relations, functions, algebraic reasoning, analysis, and technology appropriate to teach the statewide curriculum (Texas Essential Knowledge and Skills [TEKS]) in order to prepare students to use mathematics.</li>

            <li>STANDARD V: MATHEMATICAL PROCESSES: The mathematics teacher understands and uses mathematical processes to reason mathematically, to solve mathematical problems, to make mathematical connections within and outside of mathematics, and to communicate mathematically.</li>

            <li>STANDARD VI: MATHEMATICAL PERSPECTIVES: The mathematics teacher understands the historical development of mathematical ideas, the interrelationship between society and mathematics, the structure of mathematics, and the evolving nature of mathematics and mathematical knowledge.</li>

            </ul></p>
    </assemblage>

    <introduction>
        <p>In our everyday lives we encounter many circumstances which necessitate relating objects, sets, or people. Hiring is determined by comparing abilities of applicants and purchases are made based on relative prices. Descriptions such as <q>is faster than,</q> <q>is the brother of,</q> and <q>is smaller than</q> are heard countless times each day.</p>

        <p>This concept of relating elements from different collections of objects is used extensively in mathematics. In previous courses, you have considered relations primarily from a very informal perspective; we will now approach the study of relations in a more formal way and give a formal definition of a relation below. A variety of special types of relations, including functions, will be considered in greater depth in this chapter.</p>
    </introduction>

    <section xml:id="relations-section-relations">
    	<title>Relations</title>

    	<p>For convenience, we restate the definition of the Cartesian product of sets with which you might already be familiar.</p>

    	<definition>
    		<p>The <em><term>Cartesian product</term></em> of two sets <m>A</m> and <m>B</m>, denoted <m>A \times B</m>, is the set consisting of all ordered pairs in which the first element comes from set <m>A</m> and the second element comes from set <m>B</m>; that is, <m>A \times B = \{ (a,b) \mid a \in A \ \text{and} \ b \in B\}</m>.</p>
    	</definition>

    	<definition>
    		<p>A <em><term>relation</term></em> <m>R</m> from a set <m>A</m> to a set <m>B</m> is a subset of <m>A \times B</m>. If <m>R</m> is a relation from <m>A</m> to <m>A</m>, we say <m>R</m> is a relation on <m>A</m>.</p>
    	</definition>

    	<p>While a relation may be described in a variety of ways, it is really just a set of ordered pairs.</p>

    	<example xml:id="relations-example-relations">
    		<p>Let <m>A = \{a,b,c,d\}</m> and <m>B = \{1,2,3\}</m>. Consider the following sets.
    			<ol>

    				<li><m>R_1 =\{ (a,2), (b,3), (c,2), (d,3)\}</m></li>

    				<li><m>R_2 = \{ (a,1), (a, 2), (b,3) \}</m></li>

    				<li><m>R_3 = \{(a, 1), (b, 3), (c, 2) \}</m></li>

    				<li><m>R_4 = \{ (a,a), (b,b), (c,c), (d,d) \}</m></li>

    				<li><m>R_5 = \{ (d, a), (c, a), (d,d) \}</m></li>

    			</ol>
    		Each of the sets <m>R_1</m>, <m>R_2</m>, and <m>R_3</m> is a relation from <m>A</m> to <m>B</m> because the first elements in the ordered pairs are from <m>A</m> and the second elements are from <m>B</m>, while <m>R_4</m> and <m>R_5</m> are relations on <m>A</m> because both first and second elements are from <m>A</m>.</p>
    	</example>

    	<p>Although relations are actually sets of ordered pairs, such collections of ordered pairs may be indicated in many ways. Notice that a relation is essentially a pairing of elements according to some criteria. For example, we may <q>pair</q> a person's name with his or her social security number, age, height, or the names of cities lived in. Sometimes relations are specified simply by listing these pairs in set form as in the example above. When relations are described in this form, the rules or criteria for the pairing are often not known. For instance, in <m>R_1</m> of <xref ref="relations-example-relations" />, we know that <m>b</m> and <m>d</m> are both related to <m>3</m>, but we do not know why. Similarly, relations may be indicated in table or graphical form as in the below.</p>

    	<figure xml:id="figure-relations-picture">
    		<image width="80%" source="images/relations-picture.jpg">
                <description>pictorial representation R from A to B</description>
            </image>
            <caption>Pictorial representation <m>R</m> from <m>A</m> to <m>B</m></caption>
        </figure>

    	<example xml:id="relations-example-relation-picture">
    		<p><xref ref="figure-relations-picture" /> is a pictorial representation of of the relation <m>R = \{(1, 4), (6, 4), (3, 3), (10, 2)\}</m> from <m>A = \{1, 3, 6, 10\}</m> to <m>B = \{2, 3, 4\}</m>. The arrow diagram below is a different way of representing the same relation.</p>

	        <image width="40%" xml:id="relation-arrows">
                <description>arrow representation R from A to B</description>
                <latex-image>
                <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
                <![CDATA[
                \begin{tikzpicture}[scale=1]
                \draw[->] (0,0) node[left] {$10$} -- (3,2.5) node[right] {$2$};
                \draw[->] (0,1) node[left] {$6$} -- (3,0.45) node[right] {$4$}; 
                \draw[->] (0,2) node[left] {$3$} -- (3,1.5) node[right] {$3$};   
                \draw[->] (0,3) node[left] {$1$} -- (3,0.55);     
                \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                </latex-image>
            </image>

            <p>A third representation of <m>R</m> is given in table form below.</p>

        <table xml:id="table-relations-table">
           <tabular halign="center" top="medium">
                <row bottom="medium">
                    <cell><m>a</m></cell><cell><m>b</m></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>3</cell><cell>3</cell>
                </row>                <row>
                    <cell>6</cell><cell>4</cell>
                </row>                <row bottom="medium">
                    <cell>10</cell><cell>2</cell>
                </row>
           </tabular>
            <caption>A table representation <m>R</m> from <m>A</m> to <m>B</m></caption>
        </table>

    	</example>

    	<p>In many cases, listing all the ordered pairs in a relation is tedious or simply impossible. Under those circumstances the relation may be described in many different ways; associated ordered pairs are indicated by specifying a defining rule.</p>

    	<example xml:id="relations-example-relation-ordered-pairs">
    		<p>The equation <m>x + y = 4</m> describes a relation, <m>R</m>, consisting of an infinite set of ordered pairs whose components will satisfy the equation. Hence, the ordered pairs <m>(2, 2)</m>, <m>( 3/2, 5/2 )</m>, <m>(-7, 11)</m>, and <m>(0, 4)</m> are a few of the elements in the relation. Precisely stated,
    			<me>R(x,y) = \{ (x, y) \in \mathbb R \times \mathbb R \mid x + y = 4 \}</me>
    		That is, the relation described by the equation is actually the infinite set of ordered pairs of real numbers whose sum is equal to <m>4</m>. In the following figure, we have indicated all the ordered pairs which satisfy the linear equation; this is sometimes called the graphical representation of the equation.</p>

            <figure xml:id="figure-relations-graph">
                <image width="50%" source="images/relations-graph.png">
                    <description>pictorial representation R from A to B</description>
                </image>
                <caption>Graphical representation of <m>x + y = 4</m></caption>
            </figure>

    	</example>

        <example xml:id="relations-example-relation-set-builder">
            <p>Let <m>A = \{ 1, 2, 3, 4\}</m> and define a relation <m>R</m> on <m>A</m> by
                <me>R(x,y) = \{ (x, y) \in A \times A \mid x \leq y \}.</me>
            That is, <m>R</m> is the set of all ordered pairs whose components both come from the set <m>A</m> and in which the first component is less than or equal to the second. In this case we could enumerate <m>R</m> as follows:
                <me>R = \{ (1, 1), (1, 2), (1, 3), (1, 4), (2, 2), (2, 3), (2, 4), (3, 3), (3, 4), (4, 4) \}</me></p>
        </example>

        <p>Notice in <xref ref="relations-example-relation-set-builder" /> that it is merely inconvenient to have to list all the ordered pairs implied by the rule given.  However, if the set A were the set of all integers instead of the finite set <m>\{1, 2, 3, 4\}</m>, the same rule applied to A would yield an infinite set of ordered pairs that would be impossible to list. In such cases, it is convenient to use notation that refers to the relation by the criteria used for comparison. We say the relation <m>R</m> is <q>less than or equal to</q> or <q><m>\leq</m></q> rather than the actual set of ordered pairs, and instead of saying <m>(1, 3) \in R</m>, we say <m>1 \leq 3</m>.</p>

        <remark>
            <p>In general, we often substitute the notation <m>aRb</m> for <m>(a, b) \in R</m>.</p>
        </remark>

        <p>Then to determine whether two elements in the set are related, we simply substitute our familiar relation for <m>R</m> in the expression <m>aRb</m>. For example, instead of asking if the ordered pair <m>(3, 2)</m> is an element of the relation <q>is greater than,</q> we ask if <m>3</m> <q>is greater than</q> <m>2</m>; that is, we usually write <m>3 > 2</m> instead of writing <m>(3,2) \in</m> <q><m>></m></q>.</p>


        <p>In considering each of the examples given in this section, it is clear that a relation between sets <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> need not <q>use up</q> all of both sets. This idea leads us to consider those subsets of <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> whose elements are paired by the relation, namely the domain and range.</p> 

        <definition xml:id="relations-definition-domain-range">
            <p>If <m>R</m> is a relation from <m>A</m> to <m>B</m>, then the <term>domain</term> of <m>R</m>, <m>\domain(R)</m> is defined by
                <me>\domain(R) = \{a \in A \mid (a, b) \in R \text{ for some } b \in B\}.</me>
            The <term>range</term>, denoted by <m>\range(R)</m>, is defined by
                <me>\range(R) = \{b \in B \mid (a, b) \in R \text{ for some } a \in A\}.</me></p>
        </definition>

        <p>By <xref ref="relations-definition-domain-range" />, it is clear that <m>\domain(R)</m> is a subset of <m>A</m> and <m>\range(R)</m> is a subset of <m>B</m>.</p>

        <p>Informally, we designate the domain of a relation <m>R</m> as the set of all elements of the set <m>A</m> that are actually paired with (or mapped to) at least one element in <m>B</m>. The range of a relation R may be described as the set of all elements in the set <m>B</m> to which at least one element of <m>A</m> is mapped. These concepts are defined formally in the definition below.</p>

        <example xml:id="relations-example-domain-range">
            <p>Consider the sets <m>R_1, R_2, \ldots, R_5</m> as defined in <xref ref="relations-example-relations" />.  Then
                <ol>

                    <li><m>\domain(R_1) = A</m> and <m>\range(R_1) = \{ 2, 3 \}</m>.</li>


                    <li><m>\domain(R_2) = \{ a, b\}</m> and <m>\range(R_2) = B</m>.</li>

                    <li><m>\domain(R_3) = \{a, b, c\}</m> and <m>\range(R_3) = B</m>.</li>

                    <li><m>\domain(R_4) = A</m> and <m>\range(R_4) = A</m>.</li>

                    <li><m>\domain(R_5) = \{c, d \}</m> and <m>\range(R_5) = \{ a, d \}</m>.</li>


                </ol></p>
        </example>

        <example xml:id="relations-example-unit-circle">
            <p>Consider the equation <m>x^2 + y^2 = 1</m> defined on <m>\mathbb R</m>.  Let
                <me>R = \{ (x, y) \in \mathbb R \times \mathbb R \} \mid x^2 + y^2 = 1 \}.</me>
            Then <m>\domain(R) = \{ x \mid -1 \leq x \leq 1 \}</m> and <m>\range(R) = \{ y \mid -1 \leq y \leq 1 \}</m> since substituting numbers  whose squares are greater than <m>1</m> for either variable yields an equation with only complex solutions.</p>
        </example>

        <p>We will investigate the concepts of domain and range in more detail in the study of functions. However, the reader may suspect that although these sets are sometimes easily found, often they will require some insight and work to determine!</p>

        <p>Earlier we considered the relation <q><m>\leq</m>.</q> If we were to consider the associated pairs in reverse order, we might describe this new list of ordered pairs by the relation <q><m>\geq</m>.</q> Thus we see that relations are in some sense reversible, and we formalize this concept in the definition that follows.</p>

        <definition xml:id="relations-definition-inverse-relation">
            <p>If <m>R</m> is a relation from <m>A</m> to <m>B</m>, then the <term>inverse relation</term> of <m>R</m>, denoted by <m>R^{-1}</m>, is defined by
                <me>R^{-1} = \{(b, a)  \mid (a, b) \in R \}.</me></p>
        </definition>

        <p>Thus, <m>R^{-1}</m> is a new relation from <m>B</m> to <m>A</m> and consists of ordered pairs from <m>R</m> with the components reversed.  Hence, the inverse relation of <m>R = \{ (2,3), (4, 7), (2, 9), (6,9) \}</m> is the relation <m>R^{-1} = \{ (3,2), (7,4), (9,2), (9, 6) \}</m>.</p>

        <p>Consider the relation in <xref ref="figure-relations-relation-example" />.  The inverse relation <m>R^{-1}</m> from <m>B</m> to <m>A</m> can be found by simply reversing the arrows (<xref ref="figure-relations-inverse-relation-example" />).  In this case, <m>\domain(R) = \range(R^{-1}</m> and <m>\range(R) = \domain(R^{-1})</m>.</p>

        <figure xml:id="figure-relations-relation-example">
            <image width="80%" xml:id="relations-relation-example">
                <description>two overlapping circles with the common part shaded</description>
                <latex-image>
                <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
                <![CDATA[
                \begin{tikzpicture}[scale=1]
                \draw [very thick] (2,2) circle(1.5);  
                \draw [very thick] (6,2) circle(1.5); 
                \draw[->] (2,3) node [left] {$a$} -- (6,3) node [right] {$1$};
                \draw[->] (2,2.5) node [left] {$b$} -- (6,2.5) node [right] {$2$}; 
                \draw[->] (2,2.5) -- (6,2); 
                \draw[->] (2,1.5) node [left] {$d$} -- (6,1.5) node [right] {$4$};
                \draw[->] (2,1) node [left] {$e$} -- (6,2) node [right] {$3$};
                \node at (0,3) {$A$};
                \node [left] at (2,2) {$c$};
                \node at (8,3) {$B$};                                     
                \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                </latex-image>
            </image>
            <caption>The relation <m>R</m> from <m>A</m> to <m>B</m></caption>
        </figure>



        <figure xml:id="figure-relations-inverse-relation-example">
            <image width="80%" xml:id="relations-inverse-relation-example">
                <description>two overlapping circles with the common part shaded</description>
                <latex-image>
                <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
               <![CDATA[
                \begin{tikzpicture}[scale=1]
                \draw [very thick] (2,2) circle(1.5);  
                \draw [very thick] (6,2) circle(1.5); 
                \draw[<-] (2,3) node [left] {$a$} -- (6,3) node [right] {$1$};
                \draw[<-] (2,2.5) node [left] {$b$} -- (6,2.5) node [right] {$2$}; 
                \draw[<-] (2,2.5) -- (6,2); 
                \draw[<-] (2,1.5) node [left] {$d$} -- (6,1.5) node [right] {$4$};
                \draw[<-] (2,1) node [left] {$e$} -- (6,2) node [right] {$3$};
                \node at (0,3) {$A$};
                \node [left] at (2,2) {$c$};
                \node at (8,3) {$B$};                                     
                \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                </latex-image>
            </image>
            <caption>The relation <m>R^{-1}</m> from <m>B</m> to <m>A</m></caption>
        </figure>


    </section>

     <section xml:id="relations-section-equiv-relations">
        <title>Equivalence Relations</title>

        <p>One particular kind of relation that plays a vital role in mathematics is an equivalence relation. Before defining an equivalence relation, we will consider definitions and examples of each of the properties involved.</p>

        <definition xml:id="relations-definition-reflexive">
            <p>A relation <m>R</m> is  <term>reflexive</term> if <m>(a, a) \in R</m> for every <m>a \in A</m>. That is for each <m>a \in A</m>, We have <m>aRa</m>.</p>
        </definition>

        <p>It is important to realize that this definition involves a quantified expression, <q>for each <m>a \in A</m>.</q> Recall from logic that when such an expression is negated, the quantifier changes. Hence, it follows that a relation is not reflexive if there exists even one element in <m>A</m> that is not related to itself.</p>

        <example xml:id="relations-example-less-than-equal">
            <p>The relation <q><m>\leq</m></q> on <m>\mathbb Z</m> has the reflexive property since every integer is less than or equal to itself.</p>
        </example>

         <example xml:id="relations-example-equal">
            <p>The relation <q><m>=</m></q> on <m>\mathbb R</m> is reflexive since every real number is equal to itself.</p>
        </example>

         <example xml:id="relations-example-not-reflexive">
            <p>The relation <m>R = \{ (2, 3), (2,2), (3,2), (3,3) \}</m> is not a reflexive relation on the set <m>A = \{  1, 2, 3\}</m>  since <m>1 \in A</m>, but <m>(1,1) \notin R</m>. But <m>R</m> is reflexive when considered as a relation on the set <m>B = \{2, 3 \}</m>.</p>
        </example>

        <example xml:id="relations-example-power-set">
            <p>Let <m>S</m> be nonempty and <m>\mathcal P(S)</m> be the power set of <m>S</m>. Then the subset relation is reflexive on <m>\mathcal P(S)</m> since every set is a subset of itself.</p>
        </example>

        <definition xml:id="relations-definition-symmetric">
            <p>A relation <m>R</m> on <m>A</m> is  <term>symmetric</term> if whenever <m>(a, b) \in R</m>, then <m>(b,a) \in R</m>. Alternatively, if <m>aRb</m>, then <m>bRa</m>.</p>
        </definition>

        <p>You should notice a major distinction in the nature of the definitions of these terms. The definition of reflexive is universal in that it must be true for all members of the set upon which it is defined. In contrast, the definition for the symmetric property is stated in the form of a conditional. (Remember from formal logic that a conditional, <m>p \rightarrow q</m>, is false only when <m>p</m> is true and <m>q</m> is false.) So to show a relation is not symmetric we must be able to find an ordered pair <m>(a,b)</m> in <m>R</m> such that <m>(b, a)</m> is not in <m>R</m>.</p>

        <example xml:id="relations-example-symmetric">
            <p>Let <m>A = \{ 1, 2, 3, 4 \}</m> and consider the given relations on <m>A</m>.  The relations <m>R = \{ (1, 2), (2, 1), (3, 4), (4,3)\}</m> and <m>S = \{ (1,1)\}</m> have the symmetric property. However, <m>T = \{ (3,3). (2,4), (4,2), (1, 2)  \}</m> is not symmetric since <m>(1, 2) \in T</m> but <m>(2, 1) \notin T</m>.</p>
        </example>

        <p>It is important to remember that to show a relation does <em>not</em> have a certain property, we need only provide a single counterexample.</p>

        <example xml:id="relations-example-not-symmetric">
            <p>The relation <q><m>\geq</m></q> is not symmetric on <m>\mathbb R</m> since <m>5 \geq 2</m> but <m>2 \not\geq 5</m>.</p>
        </example>

        <example xml:id="relations-example-rectangles">
            <p>Let <m>A</m> be the set of rectangles in the Cartesian plane, and let elements of <m>A</m> be related if they have the same area.  Then this relation is symmetric.</p>
        </example>

        <definition xml:id="relations-definition-transitive">
            <p>A relation <m>R</m> on <m>A</m> is <term>transitive</term> if whenever <m>(a, b) \in R</m> and <m>(b, c) \in R</m>, then <m>(a, c) \in R</m>.</p>
        </definition>

        <p>A relation <m>R</m> is not transitive if there exist <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>c</m> in <m>A</m> such that <m>(a,b) \in R</m>  and <m>(b, c) \in R</m> but <m>(a, c) \notin R</m>.</p>

        <example xml:id="relations-example-less-than">
            <p>The relation <q><m>\lt</m></q> is transitive on <m>\mathbb R</m>.</p>
        </example>

        <example xml:id="relations-example-transitive">
            <p>Let <m>R = \{  (1, 1), (2, 2), (3,3) \}</m> on <m>\mathbb Z</m>. Then <m>R</m> is transitive since there do not exist integers <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>c</m> such that <m>(a,b) \in R</m>  and <m>(b, c) \in R</m> but <m>(a, c) \notin R</m>.</p>
        </example>

        <example xml:id="relations-example-not-transitive">
            <p>Let <m>R = \{  (1, 2), (2, 3) \}</m> on <m>\mathbb Z</m>. Then <m>R</m> is not transitive since <m>(1, 2) \in R</m> and <m>(2, 3) \in R</m> but <m>(1,3) \notin R</m>.</p>
        </example>

        <definition xml:id="relations-definition-equivalence-relation">
            <p>A relation <m>R</m> on <m>A</m> which is reflexive, symmetric, and transitive is called an <term>equivalence relation</term> on <m>A</m>.  If two elements <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> are equivelent, we write <m>a \sim b</m>, unless of course there is already a notation in place such as <q><m>=</m>.</q></p>
        </definition>

        <example xml:id="relations-example-not-equivalence-not-reflexive">
            <p>Let <m>A = \{ 1, 2, 3\}</m> and <m>R = \{  (1, 1), (2, 2) \}</m>. Then <m>R</m> is not an equivalence relation on <m>A</m>.  The relation is both transitive and symmetric but is not reflexive  since <m>(3, 3) \notin R</m>.</p>
        </example>


        <example xml:id="relations-example-not-equivalence-not-transitive">
            <p>Let <m>A = \{ 1, 2, 3\}</m> and
                <me>S = \{  (1, 1), (2, 2), (3,3), (1, 2), (2,1), (2, 3), (3,2) \}.</me>
            The relation <m>S</m> is both reflexive and symmetric but is not transitive, since <m>(1, 2) \in S</m> and <m>(2, 3) \in S</m> but <m>(1, 3) \notin S</m>.</p>
        </example>

        <example xml:id="relations-example-power-set-not-equivalence">
            <p>Let <m>A = \{a, b\}</m> and <m>\mathcal P(A)</m> be the power set of <m>A</m>. Then the subset relation is reflexive  and transitive  but is not symmetric since <m>\{a\} \subseteq \{a, b\}</m> but <m>\{a, b\} \not\subseteq \{a\}</m>.</p>
        </example>



        <example xml:id="relations-example-integers-mod5">
            <p>Consider the set <m>\mathbb Z</m> and define <m>a \sim b</m> if <m>5</m> divides <m>a - b</m>, denoted by <m>5 \mid (a - b)</m>; i.e., there is no remainder when <m>a - b</m> is divided by <m>5</m>. Then <m>2 \sim 12</m>, since <m>5 \mid (2 - 12)</m> and <m>3 \not\sim 7</m>, since <m>5 \not\mid (3 - 7)</m>.  We have defined an eqiuivalence relation on <m>\mathbb Z</m>.  The proof is left as an exercise (<xref ref="relations-exercise-integers-mod5" />).</p>
        </example>

        <example xml:id="relations-example-integers-modn">
            <p>Consider the set <m>\mathbb Z</m>, and let <m>n</m> be a fixed integer that is not equal to zero.  define <m>a \sim b</m> if <m>n \mid (a - b)</m>.  The relation is a generalization of <xref ref="relations-example-integers-mod5" /> and is also an equivalence relation.</p>
        </example>

        <example>
            <p>Some other equivalence relations are <q>is the same age as</q> on the set of all people, <q>has the same area as</q> on the set of all rectangles in the Cartesian plane, and <q>lives on the same street as</q> on the set of all people living in a given city.</p>

        </example>

        <p>Consider the relation <q>is the same age as</q> on the set of all students in a given class. This relation groups the people in the class according to age. Each person in the class is in some group, even if it is a single member group. In addition, no person is in more than one group and all people in a specific group are the same age. These qualities are common to all equivalence relations, leading us to the following formal definition.</p>

        <definition xml:id="relations-definition-equivalence-class">
            <p>Let <m>\sim</m> be an equivalence relation on <m>A</m>. If <m>x \in A</m>, then the <term>equivalence class</term> of <m>x</m>, denoted by <m>\overline{x}</m>, is defined by <m>\overline{x} = \{ y \in A \mid x \sim y \}</m>.</p>
        </definition>

        <example xml:id="relations-example-equivalence-class">
            <p>Suppose <m>A = \{ 6, 7, 8, 9, 10\} </m> and let the relation <m>R</m> on <m>A</m> be defined by <m>aRb</m> if <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> have the same remainder when divided by <m>2</m>. This relation is an equivalence relation since it is reflexive, symmetric, and transitive. (Verification is left as an exercise.) Then by <xref ref="relations-definition-equivalence-class" />, 
                <me>\overline{6} = \overline{8} = \overline{10} = \{6, 8, 10\}</me>
            and 
                <me>\overline{7} = \overline{9} = \{7, 9\}.</me>
            Furthermore, <m>\overline{6}</m> and <m>\overline{7}</m> are disjoint sets whose union is <m>A</m>. So <m>A</m> has just partitioned into disjoint pieces where each piece can have different names.</p>
        </example>

        <p>The observations for the specific relation considered in <xref ref="relations-example-equivalence-class" /> lead us to generalize these concepts to any equivalence relation defined on an arbitrary set.</p>

        <theorem  xml:id="relations-theorem-equivalence-class">
            <statement>
                <p>Let <m>\sim</m> be an equivalence relation on <m>A</m>. Then:
                    <ol>

                        <li>Each equivalence class is non-empty.</li>

                        <li>Any two equivalence classes are either equal or disjoint</li>

                        <li>The set <m>A</m> is equal to the union of all the equivalence classes.</li>

                    </ol>
                </p>
            </statement>
        </theorem>

        <p>When given an equivalence relation on a set, we may find the classes generated by that relation by first choosing elements at random from the set. For example, suppose
            <me>A = \left\{ \frac{2}{3}, -\frac{1}{2}, -1, 0, \frac{4}{6}, \frac{0}{3}, - \frac{4}{8}, \frac{10}{15} \right\}.</me>
        and let the equivalence relation on be <q><m>=</m>.</q>  To find the equivalence classes determined by the relation, we may choose any element in <m>A</m>, say <m>4/6</m>.  Then <m>4/6 \in \overline{4/6}</m>, since <m>4/6 = 4/6</m>.  The other elements of <m>\overline{4/6}</m> are <m>2/3</m> and <m>10/15</m>, since they are the only elements of <m>A</m> equal to <m>4/6</m>.  Thus, <m>\overline{4/6} = \{ 4/6, 2/3, 10/15 \}</m>.  Part (2) of <xref ref="relations-theorem-equivalence-class" /> implies we might just as easily have chosen <m>2/3></m> or <m>10/15</m>, and we would have arrived at the same equivalence class.  That is, since <m>2/3 \in \overline{4/6}</m> and <m> 10/15 \in\overline{4/6}</m>, then <m>\overline{2/3} = \overline{4/6} = \overline{10/15}</m>. So we conclude that we may designate an equivalence class completely using any of its elements.</p> 

        <exercises>

            <exercise xml:id="exercise-relations-mod-5">
                <statement>
                    <p>Prove the relation described in <xref ref="relations-example-integers-mod5" /> is an equivalence relation.</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>


            <exercise xml:id="exercise-relations-mod-n">
                <statement>
                    <p>Prove the relation described in <xref ref="relations-example-integers-modn" /> is an equivalence relation.</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>

            <exercise xml:id="exercise-relations-mod-n">
                <statement>
                    <p>Prove the relation described in <xref ref="relations-example-equivalence-class" /> is an equivalence relation.</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>

        </exercises>

    </section>


    <section xml:id="relations-section-functions">
        <title>Functions and Cardinality</title>

        <p>dnfkjdjfk</p>

 

    </section>


</chapter>
